Horror has been having a moment.
While original films in every other
genre have almost completely disappeared
from the top box office slots,
horror is bigger than ever.
People go in droves to join the ritual
of sitting in a dark room with strangers
to face their fears.
>> You're scaring me.
>> So far this year, the only completely
original live-action movie in the box
office top 10 is Obsession, which
exploded out of nowhere thanks to word
of mouth. Last year, the only original
film in the box office top 10 was the
action horror movie Sinister. To find
another original, you have to go all the
way down to number 16, where you'll find
Weapons, also a horror film. But if we
rewind to 1997,
you'll find the box office top 10 full
of original genre movies, like the
comedy Liar Liar, the romance My [music]
Best Friend's Wedding, and the action
film Air Force One.
In the top 20 that year, we also had
Contact, an original sci-fi, the sports
drama Jerry Maguire, the thriller
Conspiracy Theory, and the action movies
Face/Off and Con Air.
But over the last 30 years, the original
genre film has been slowly killed off
with one notable exception.
Whether it's Nope, Get Out, A Quiet
Place, The Black Phone, Talk to Me, Us,
Smile, M3GAN, Longlegs, or Weapons,
original horror still finds huge box
office success where other genres are
struggling.
>> Wait.
>> There have been occasional breakouts in
other genres over the last decade, but
these one-off genre hits, like the
comedy Free Guy or the war movie 1917,
are pretty few and far between and feel
more like the exception that proves the
rule. Even with the success of one of
these movies, we don't see a resurgence
in the genre overall. If you've been
watching my channel for a while, you
know I want to know, why is it like
this? Who killed the genre film? And
perhaps more importantly, why do
audiences love horror more than ever.
>> What is so wrong? And why do they do
that? It's too
>> Of course, I know that movies and genres
besides horror still get made. I'm
making a distinction between genre as a
label that we use to categorize movies
and the genre film where the audience
goes to a movie in part for what the
genre itself provides. Take superhero
movies as an example. They do have some
recognizable traits and structure, but
I'd argue that what draws people to the
latest Superman movie or MCU film isn't
that it's a superhero movie. They're not
going for the structure of the genre.
>> There's a new Marvel out that's supposed
to be nuts. We should go see that.
>> They're going for the fact that it's a
Superman movie or the latest installment
in the ongoing story that is the MCU.
And the fact that other than Josh
Trank's 2012 found footage movie
Chronicle, we haven't seen a single
successful superhero film that isn't
based on existing IP, I think helps make
this case. Movies from other genres
still show up in theaters, but if we
look at what succeeds in each of these
genres, it's usually not the genre
itself that is the primary selling
point. Take for example F1. Does it owe
its success to the fact that it's a
sports movie
or is it the draw of Brad Pitt and the
Formula 1 brand?
>> [music]
>> Or look at something like Oppenheimer,
which isn't really original anyway since
it's based on a book. But did it make a
billion bucks because it's a biopic or
because it's a Christopher Nolan movie?
Even [music] if it succeeded as a
biopic, are people really going to see
biopics because they just love biopics
as a genre
or because they're drawn by the subject
of the biopic? And for the straight
dramas that succeed, almost all of them
do so not because of the genre, but
because of the director, star power, or
awards buzz that they managed to
generate. It hasn't always been this
way, though. For much of film history,
it wouldn't have been strange to go to a
movie just because you wanted to see a
movie in that genre. You might describe
a new movie by saying, "Have you seen
the latest Western?" These days we're
way more likely to say, "Have you seen
the new Nolan? Have you seen the new
Star Wars movie?" or even, "Have you
seen the new A24?"
But there's one major holdout. Horror
movies can still come out of nowhere
with a new director, relatively unknown
cast, original idea, and draw a huge
crowd to the theater for no other reason
than being a good horror movie. But
before we can understand why and how
horror survived, we have to look at who
or what killed everything else.
>> Off to see the wizard.
>> Classic Hollywood was built on the genre
film, musicals, melodramas, screwball
comedies, noirs, [music] and gangster
pictures.
>> going to take it?
>> In the 1950s, there was an explosion of
low-budget sci-fi movies and big-budget
epics.
But then in the '70s,
something started to change.
Spielberg's Jaws became the first movie
to make over $100 million at the
domestic box office, permanently
altering Hollywood's brain chemistry.
Studios realized that if you had a movie
with a really simple hook, marketed to
the gills, and did a wide release in the
summer, you could make serious money.
This was the birth of the high-concept
blockbuster era, which Spielberg himself
allegedly described by saying, "If a
person can tell me the idea in 25 words
or less,
it's going to make a pretty good movie."
And over the next 30 years, as long as a
movie had a punchy high-concept logline,
original ideas across a bunch of genres
were able to find blockbuster success.
This is the era that gave us movies like
Die Hard, Groundhog Day, and Back to the
Future. But this era was the start of
something else, as well.
Studios looked at a movie like Jaws 2,
which had mixed reviews, [music]
no Steven Spielberg, and was the
continuation of a story that had already
wrapped up pretty neatly. They still let
make over 200 million worldwide, and
they realized that a movie with a
recognizable name could sell as well as
any star, director, or high-concept
logline.
You know where this is headed, but the
change didn't happen overnight. Studios
used some of the massive profits from
their predictably successful tentpole
films to fund specialty divisions that
took risks [music] on more
unconventional mid-budget original genre
films, like the crime thriller Seven
from New Line or a romantic comedy like
Shakespeare in Love from Miramax. By
2005, [music]
while the franchise and IP-based films
had already gobbled up a lot of box
office real estate, there was still room
for original genre movies like the
comedy Wedding Crashers, romantic comedy
Hitch, or action movie Mr. and Mrs.
Smith.
But by the late 2000s, as the financial
crisis hit, DVD sales evaporated, and
streaming services started to challenge
[music] theatrical attendance, studios
became more and more risk-averse,
ruthlessly cutting out everything but
the most [music] guaranteed hits.
Original movies like comedies, romance,
and adult dramas, high-concept or not,
just weren't safe bets anymore. They
didn't sell well overseas, [music] they
didn't convert into franchises, and the
specialty divisions that once made them
got cut. And while the studios were
cutting back on comedies, dramas, and
romance films, these more
dialogue-focused genres were blossoming
in the new golden age of TV and the rise
of streaming that followed. Streaming
also [music] killed the DVD rental
market, which had been funding original
genre hits for years.
>> What happened? What happened?
>> A movie like Fight Club could flop in
theaters, but then more than make back
its budget thanks to DVD rentals.
[music]
Genre pieces like Michael Mann's
Blackhat, Guy Ritchie's spy thriller The
Man from U.N.C.L.E., or Shane Black's
buddy comedy The Nice [music] Guys all
thrived in this rental market.
Studios like Netflix, Apple, and Amazon
Prime didn't just [music] destroy the
DVD rental market, they swooped in and
took over the production of these kinds
of genre action and comedy hits. Some of
these movies are still getting made, but
studios give them little to no
theatrical run and dump them straight
onto streaming, so they've all but
disappeared from the box office
landscape. [music]
But how come during all of this, while
every other genre film was being picked
off one by one, horror didn't just
escape death, but grew stronger than
ever.
What makes a good horror movie? You
might want some interesting social
commentary, an original catchy idea,
inventive visuals, maybe a good cast.
Quality filmmaking is always a plus, a
sense of atmosphere.
But ultimately, the bargain of horror as
a genre is that it promises to deliver
an experience, to evoke something
[music] very primal,
to unsettle you, to cause anxiety, fear,
or terror.
And why is that the thing that breaks
records while many other indie genre
films struggle to even get recognized?
Some of the story might just be boring
old economics and marketing.
Relative to some genres like action and
science fiction, a horror movie that
delivers well on the promise of the
genre can be made relatively affordably.
The budgetary limitations that might
hurt other genres can even help horror
movies. Despite being made for less than
a million dollars, a movie like
Obsession never feels cheap or small. If
anything, it's contained reality adds to
the horrifying atmosphere. Limited
locations might help evoke a sense of
claustrophobia. Unknown actors can
immerse you in a fiction and add a a of
vulnerability. Shadowy, moody lighting
doesn't just serve the story, it can
also help cover over more affordable
production design. And done well, the
suggestion of a monster can be far
scarier than the most expensive CGI
creations. On top of being cheap to
make, horror movies are easier to
market. Most of them are almost high
concept by definition, and the fact that
they often rely on incredibly evocative
visuals means that their trailers are
more attention-grabbing in a visually
[music] saturated media landscape. And
with the core function of the genre
driven not by dialogue, but atmosphere,
mood, and visuals, a lot of horror plays
well on international markets. Horror's
reliance on activating [music] our
primal human instinct means it's
universal in a way that more
linguistically and culturally specific
genres like romantic comedies aren't
always. And horror movies tend to
convert well into IP with long-term
success. Even though we see more
original horror than any other original
category, we also see a ton of
successful horror franchises. So, for
studios and independent production
companies, horror is one of the cheaper
genre options they can bet on that still
has massive potential upside. But, I
don't think this tells the whole story.
I don't think audiences are just passive
consumers greedily gobbling anything the
studios will shove down their throats.
The biggest thing that propelled the
success of Obsession was word of mouth.
If marketing budget alone decided box
office return, Backrooms wouldn't have
smashed the latest Star Wars film. On
some level, if we didn't want them, we'd
go spend our hard-earned $15 somewhere
else. So, why have audiences chosen
horror as the defining genre of our era?
Why horror now?
>> At first glance,
everything looked the same.
It wasn't.
Something evil had taken possession of
the town.
>> You could study the cultural currents
[music] of the last 75 years of American
history through its horror films. In the
'50s, Cold War paranoia manifested in
fears of dehumanization, like the
brain-dead pod people of Invasion of the
Body Snatchers.
>> were now hosts harboring an alien form
of life, a cosmic form, which to survive
must take over every human man.
>> Or apocalyptic destruction as seen in
them, which unleashed giant radioactive
ants on American cities.
>> Because unless you solve it, man as the
dominant species of life on Earth will
probably be extinct.
>> The Vietnam-stained new horror of the
1970s was soaked in arbitrary brutality,
distrust of authority, and at times,
like with The Last House on the Left and
The Texas Chainsaw Massacre, outright
nihilism.
The Reaganite '80s saw a wave of
slashers, like Friday the 13th and
Halloween. These franchises pitted
aspirations of youth liberation against
the paternalistic conservative morality
of the time.
>> get smart.
>> Me?
>> You blame everything on kids.
>> These are just a few of the many
undercurrents that can be traced.
Stephen King, in his 1981 treatise on
horror, Danse Macabre, wrote, "The
horror genre has often been able to find
national phobic pressure points. And
those books and films which have been
the most successful almost always seem
to play upon and express fears which
exist across a wide spectrum of people."
Sometimes horror can be made and sold
explicitly with these allegories in
mind. Someone like Jordan Peele can use
a movie like Get Out to examine the
horror of racism in America.
But other times, these cultural
anxieties are translated through horror
more unconsciously. George Romero, who
made The Night of the Living Dead, has
denied that any allegory in the movie
was intentional. But the film, through
both Romero's direction and its
popularity with audiences still managed
to tap into latent anxieties about a
polarized 1960s American society
cannibalizing itself. Whether
intentional or not, horror is an
expressionistic medium. It uses imagery,
situations, symbols, and worlds to both
express and tap into the prevailing
cultural fears and societal [music]
anxieties. Obsession explores the horror
of coercive romance and sexual assault.
And it's not surprising to me that it's
resonated with a young audience amidst
the rise of heightened anxiety
surrounding dating and romance.
It makes sense that the 2011 virus
horror contagion saw a resurgence during
COVID.
>> Can I call someone?
>> Call everyone.
>> But why do we seek out horror movies
about things we're already afraid of?
>> You see her.
You have to see her, I'm bleeding.
Holly, tell me that you need somebody.
>> I think it's because anxiety and fear
are incredibly repressed [music] in our
society. Want to see anger? Just go
online. Sadness? We often collectively
mourn, though perhaps not as well as we
could. But I find it's rare to hear
someone openly acknowledge [music]
their fears and anxieties.
In her book Feeding the Monster, the
author and film critic Anna Bogutskaya
[music]
writes that horror is not about simple
voyeurism, about looking at someone
being butchered or haunted.
It's about feeling what they're feeling.
>> [panting]
>> Horror provides a contained outlet, an
experience of gathering together
socially to literally face our fears,
where the point is not repressing the
fear, but to finally actually let
yourself feel it.
Getting to feel repressed fear
collectively in a contained context that
we consent to, where we know we won't
actually be harmed by what we're seeing,
serves a powerful psychological function
in our society.
And there's an unapologetic sense of
sincerity found at the core of horror.
As Bog Iger Scatzia says, there's
nothing ironic about being scared. It is
at its best an experience of extreme
physical and emotional earnestness.
Perhaps we find this to be a potent
salve to the post-modern milieu of
modern life where everything is drenched
in layers of irony, self-apology, and
self-referentialism.
Perhaps it's an attempt to do a kind of
collective shadow work to exercise the
demons that we fear by bringing them
into the light of the cinema screen.
Maybe all of this helps society. Maybe
it's a distraction, an emotional release
valve that lets off steam while we
continue to avoid addressing the real
problems underlying these fears. Culture
is slippery and nebulous. It's
impossible to boil the success of a
genre down to one thing. But I think
what all these explanations have in
common is that they point to horror as a
form of cultural expressionism. Stephen
King said, "Terror often arises from a
pervasive sense of disestablishment,
that things are in the unmaking."
And is there a better way to describe
the last 15 years or so, the time during
which the success of horror has been on
the rise?
I bet you feel it, too. The sense that
the world is being unmade, that you're
not quite sure what it's being turned
into or who it's being unmade for.
So, is it any surprise that in a time of
increasing social and cultural anxiety
where we're facing down the barrel of a
global system that seems to be nearing a
state of collapse
all while we feel increasingly powerless
to get those with power to do anything
to change course, where we have no
accepted outlet to fully feel or express
the fear that comes along with living in
this reality,
that horror movies are the most
successful genre left at the box office.
I've been writing my own horror movie
this year, and something that has helped
me write is creating a mood board that
captures the look and feel of the scenes
I'm writing. This has been super easy to
do with Frame Set, my sponsor for this
video.
>> [music]
>> Frame Set is a tool that helps
filmmakers find inspiration, expand
their vision, and communicate their
ideas visually. You can quickly and
easily search through a huge library of
stills and motion images from movies,
music videos, commercials, and more. You
can then download these images, save
them to sets, and share them with
others. The search function works really
well. In addition to searching for
specific films, actors, or directors,
you can also just describe the subject
or style of a shot. And if you find an
image you like, you can easily browse
through similar shots. I used Frame Set
to quickly build a reference board
[music] that I gave to the colorist for
my documentary feature, Out of a Flood,
and it's a great research tool for video
essays where I'm studying a specific
style, type of shot, or looking for a
specific moment from a film. Frame Set
is like having a cinematography search
engine for a ton of great films at your
fingertips. And you can go give it a try
right now. With the free version, you'll
get 10 searches a day, or you can click
the link in the description [music]
below to support my channel when you
upgrade to Pro for faster high-res
browsing and unlimited searches. Big
thanks to Frame Set for building such a
great tool for filmmakers [music]
and for sponsoring this video.